<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A firebrand pluckt out of the burning. A sermon preached at Margarets Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons, at their late solemn fast, Novemb. 27. 1644. By Benjamin Pickering, Minister of Gods Word at Buckstead in Sussex: and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of the said house.</title>
            <author>Pickering, Benjamin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E23_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860515</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E23[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A firebrand pluckt out of the burning. A sermon preached at Margarets Westminster, before the Honourable House of Commons, at their late solemn fast, Novemb. 27. 1644. By Benjamin Pickering, Minister of Gods Word at Buckstead in Sussex: and a member of the Assembly of Divines. Published by order of the said house.</title>
                  <author>Pickering, Benjamin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. L. for Philemon Stephens, and Samuel Gellibrand in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645[ie 1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the 5 in imprint date is crossed out and altered to 1644.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zechariah III, 2 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FIREBRAND PLUCKT OUT OF THE BVRNING.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> before the Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, at their late ſolemn Faſt, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 27. 1644.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Benjamin Pikering, <hi>Miniſter of Gods Word at</hi> Buckſtead <hi>in</hi> Suſſex: <hi>and a Member of the Aſſembly of Divines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order of the ſaid Houſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 50.33, 34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord of hoſtes: The children of Iſrael, and the children of Judah <hi>were</hi> oppreſſed together, and all that took them captives, held them faſt, they refuſed to let them goe.</p>
               <p>Their Redeemer <hi>is</hi> ſtrong. The LORD of hoſtes <hi>is</hi> his Name, he ſhall throughly plead their cauſe, that he may give reſt to the land, and diſquiet the inhabitants of Babylon.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Gellibrand</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:112637:1"/>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Die Mercurii</hi> 27. Novem. 1644.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament: That Maſter <hi>Sallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wey,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Knightley,</hi> doe from this Houſe give thanks to Maſter <hi>Pikering,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Gipps,</hi> for the great paines they took in the Sermons they preached this day at the intreatie of this Houſe, at S. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets Weſtminſter:</hi> It being the day of Publique Humiliation; and to deſire them to Print their Sermons. And it is Ordered that none ſhall preſume to Print their or either of their Sermons without leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their or either of their Hand-writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſying Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I Appoint <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Gellibrand,</hi> to print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>BEN. PIKERING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112637:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112637:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> Aſſembled in Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onourable Senators, Your patient attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto, and thankefull acceptance of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving paines in this Sermon (now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your Order printed, and in all humility preſented unto you) emboldens me againe to reinforce my exhortation that you would be of good courage, and goe on zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly to work with God, untill he be pleaſed to make you and all Gods people happy and bleſſed in ordaining peace, perfecting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and working all your workes for you.</p>
            <p>Nothing is ſo preiudiciall to your proceedings, nothing ſo much hinders good things from us, as many grievous provoking ſinnes in the midſt of us. Hence is it that when peace and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with Truth in purity have beene flowing in toward us as a River, the Lord hath cauſed them as <hi>Iordan</hi> to be driven back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: the night ſeemed to be paſt, and the day of the glorious Goſpel with peace on earth ſeemed to ſpread it ſelfe over us; but now the ſhadowes are againe ſtretched out, black clouds hang over our heads, ſtill threatening a day of darkeneſſe and gloomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>The profaneneſſe and incorrigibleneſſe of the multitude de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that we are ripe for iudgement, indiſpoſed and unfit for
<pb facs="tcp:112637:3"/>ſuch mercies as have beene ever ſince the happy beginning of your ſitting tendering themſelves unto us: The vitals of this Kingdome are fearefully diſtempered, the whole head is ſick and the whole heart faint: Our ſinfull diſtempers threaten the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the whole body: Therefore through the wrath of the Lord of Hoſts is the Land darkened, and the people are as fuel for fire, and their carkaſſes lye torne in the midſt of the ſtreets: for all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill.</p>
            <p>Certainly it will be acceptable to God, available to the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Land, and reducing us to a fitneſſe for Reformation, if you could, as you have begun, ſet up a faithfull Miniſtery, and eſtabliſh iudgement and iuſtice in the Gates. If iudgement had its free courſe in Citie and Countrey, the courſe of Gods iudgements would determine. Let your zeale for the Lord burne; and this burning which the Lord hath kindled would be quenched. <hi>Phinehas</hi> ſtood up and executed iudgement, and the plague ceaſed.</p>
            <p>Let not the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> ſay, <hi>There is no law now:</hi> Let them not be as when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> every man do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which was right in his owne eyes: let them know that the Kingly power reſides in his High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Let your terrour be on all the wicked: bring the wheele upon them, or make them flee into deſolate places to cut up the mallowes by the buſhes,<note place="margin">Job 30.</note> and Juniper roots for their meate. If iniquitie were purged and the wicked tooke away, God would leave off melting,<note place="margin">Jer. 6.</note> Satan would be rebuked, the enemies unarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: no weapon formed againſt you ſhould proſper.</p>
            <p>Every knowne ſinne ſuffered amongſt us, if not prevented nor puniſhed by you, will be as yours, and will give the enemie advantages:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. Moral.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20.</note> Therefore ſome thinke that Satan is ſaid to ſtand at <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> right hand, and ſo of his fellow reformers, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving iuſt accuſation, and therefore too hard for <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and his fellowes: <hi>Nam dextra fortius aliquid &amp; majus ſignificat:</hi> to this purpoſe they bring that in the <hi>109. Pſalme,</hi> Let Satan ſtand at his right hand, and thus expound it: <hi>fac ut Satan in judicio ſuperiores habeat partes:</hi> The reaſon why they thus thought was, becauſe <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did not carefully overſee and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct
<pb facs="tcp:112637:3"/>the people in <hi>Babylon;</hi> he was not zealous in exciting to the building of Gods Temple: And although we read not that he was faulty in marrying a ſtrange woman, (as ſome ſay, (but without Scripture) he did) yet this was accounted his ſinne that his brethren and ſomes by his neglect or ſufferance had done ſo,<note place="margin">Rabb. &amp; Hieron. <hi>As</hi> Sanctius <hi>hath it.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ezra 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre this is uſefull; to excite you to prevent ſinne in others, and to take away occaſion from all that ſeeke occaſion either to aſperſe, or hinder your pious proceedings in building the Lords Houſe, and ſetting up his Worſhip and Ordinances in puritie: O be carefull leſt the Adverſary get advantage; for you are not ignorant of his devices.</p>
            <p>Iuſtice alſo requires that you ſhould make ſpeed to heare and to releeve the innocent that cry to heaven, that cry to you as Gods on earth; let not their eyes faile with waiting.</p>
            <p>Be zealous for Chriſts cauſe: delay not to eſtabliſh his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and diſcipline with vigour: proceed ſo on in your reforming and treating, that glory may dwell in our Land; that mercy and truth, righteouſneſſe and peace may meete together, and kiſſe each other.</p>
            <p>Let your wiſdome find out a way ſo, that for circumſtantiall differences there be no rent made by thoſe who are one body: The wiſdome which is from above, which is pure and peaceable, ſo direct you, that you may take away all pretences of ſeparation or ſchiſme; that every mouth may be ſtopt, that brethren may dwell together in unitie, ſerving the Lord with one ſhoulder; that the God of love and peace may be amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Your religious approbation, and expediting of the Directory for Gods worſhip, is no ſmall refreſhing to the ſpirits of all the godly: you have gone farre, but forget the things that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and preſſe on toward the marke: So long as the Iewiſh builders and reformers minded more themſelves and their owne houſes then the Houſe of God, Satan prevailed by the Kings wicked Counſellours in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the <hi>Samaritancs</hi> about <hi>Iudea,</hi> to hinder their counſels and endeavours: you have given good proofe that you exalt God, and preferre his glory with the hazard of the depreſſing of your ſelves and yours. (The Lord is faithfull who will not forget your unparallel'd zeale and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:112637:4"/>of love) Continue in your integritie, and the Lord will continue a Sunne and ſhield to you;<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.14.</note> he will for your ſakes rebuke Princes; he will rebuke Satan and all his malignant Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that they ſhall be as ſtill as a ſtone: Although Satan be at your right hand, feare not, ſo long as our Mediatour ſits at the right hand of God: feare not, if you (with <hi>Ioſhua</hi>) ſtand before the Angel of the Covenant: continue to ſtand before him as your Maſter whoſe worke you are about, expecting what he will preſcribe, or enioyne. Continue in his worke, that you may be found ſo doing; ſo acquit your ſelves, that he may ſay, Well done good and faithfull ſervants, you have beene faithfull in all my houſe, enter into your Maſters ioy. Stand before this Angels as your Iudge, to whom in all your iuſt proceedings you may appeale and have reliefe. Stand before him as your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, who hath undertaken the Patronage of your righteous cauſe, and the promoting of your pious undertakings in heaven with his Father; there he ſpeakes good; there he pleads for you: and the Lord will anſwer him with good words, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble words concerning you, and concerning his <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> To his powerfull Patronage, conſtant care, and gracious guidance, you and all your weightie Affaires are commended in the daily prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt unworthy, but faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and humble ſervant, BEN. PIKERING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112637:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, at their late Solemn Faſt, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 27. 1644.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Zach. 3. latter part verſ. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Is not this a brand pluckt out of the fire?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the Lords pleaſure that the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Church many times ſhould be ſuch, as the Prophet expreſſeth: <hi>I beheld the earth, and lo, it</hi> was <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forme and void:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>and the heavens</hi> had no <hi>light.</hi> Thus it was with Gods people in the Babyloniſh cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie: Heaven and Earth, Church and Common-wealth, were in a confuſion.</p>
            <p>It is the Lords goodneſſe to have reſpect to his people in ſuch extreamities, and when all is in a Chaos, to ſtirre up helps and wayes to a new Creation of this heaven and earth.</p>
            <p>The God of the ſpirits of all fleſh, for this end ſtirs up the ſpirit of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> to give way, and of <hi>Zerubbabel, Ioſhua,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112637:5"/>Ezra,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> to revive the ſtones out of the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh to build the Citie and Temple, and to ſet up the true worſhip and pure ordinances of God.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable, that the beſt undertakings, meet with greateſt diſcouragements<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As theſe Builders and Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did; both from the Kings Courtiers and Malignant neighbours, ſtirred up by the Devill: Therefore leſt they ſhould faint and be weary, leſt their ſpirits ſhould faile, the Lord ſends encouragements by his Prophets, <hi>Haggai,</hi> and <hi>Zachary.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 5.1.</note> The like oppoſitions (much Honoured) you have had, and ſuch encouragements the Lord hath not been wanting in to you.</p>
            <p>This Prophet <hi>Zachary:</hi> Firſt, to fit and diſpoſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for mercy, exhorteth to repentance: Thus is a people prepared for the Lord. Secondly, by ſevetall viſions, the Lord firſt ſheweth how he had dealt with them, that is, with moderation, not according to their deſerts, but in meaſure and much mercy, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. &amp; 2. Secondly, for their comfort, he declareth how he would deale with them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. &amp; 7. that is, he would deale graciouſly with them, if they would turne to him, and build his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſet up his worſhip and ordinances in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p>In this third <hi>Chapter,</hi> is ſet down the fourth viſion, which the Lord manifeſted to this Prophet, that is, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the high Prieſt, and Satan ſtanding at his right hand. In <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> the high Prieſt, a type of Chriſt, is ſet out the reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Church, and Prieſthood, and true worſhip.</p>
            <p>He ſtood before the Angel of the Lord, that is, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon of the Trinitie, called the Angel of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. of this <hi>Chapter,</hi> Iehovah, attending his commands, expecting his ayde: he was in vile raiment, not as the high Prieſt of old; though the Prieſthood and Church be in a vile deſpicable condition, you ſee it is in Chriſts eye, he hath care of it. Satan an adverſary ſtands at his right hand to reſiſt. The devill will ſtill be hindering the acting hand in the things of God: Our Saviour found
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112637:5"/>it ſo, when firſt he entred upon the worke of a Mediatour, and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in his pious intentions:<note place="margin">Matth. 4. 1 Theſſ. 1.</note> Satan hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us.</p>
            <p>The Devill hateth all Divine Order and pure Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, therefore he reſiſts <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> in whom the Prieſthood and Divine worſhip were reſtored.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. the Lord is pleaſed to grant a threefold encouragement to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and the reſt, which is alſo a threefold diſcouragement to the adverſary.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Lord hath choſen Ieruſalem, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery appointed to gather and build up his people: and the Lord by deliverance of his people hath manifeſted his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection: therefore he will not forſake thoſe whom hee hath choſen: Gods chooſing is loving, <hi>Iacob</hi> have I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Whom God loves he loves to the end: therefore feare not.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Sonne of God undertakes the Patronage of his Church, he prayeth for them, he makes interceſſion to Iehovah God the Father: Iehovah ſaid, Iehovah rebuke thee: and obſerving the reduplication, the Lord rebuke thee, even the Lord that hath choſen Ieruſalem rebuke thee, we may ſee vehemency of affection in our Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour toward his Church and choſen: he was heard alway whileſt he was upon earth:<note place="margin">Joh. 11.</note> Father I know thou heareſt me alwayes. Therefore now he is at the right hand of God he is heard; The Lord will rebuke the adverſary, and anſwer this angel with good and comfortable words concerning Ieruſalem: This was to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and the reſt, and is to you another ſingular encouragement.</p>
            <p>The third is, in the words of the Text read unto you: that is, preſent reſcue: This manifeſts what Gods purpoſe is toward his people: he hath delivered them out of a wofull captivitie likely to conſume them, as a brand out of the fire, therefore the Lord will ſave them to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt; hath he begun and ſhall he not finiſh? what worke he begins he will perfect it, the Lord will perfect that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112637:6"/>which concerneth his choſen:<note place="margin">Pſal. 138.8.</note> Thus may the Lords choſen inſtruments and ſervants be encouraged: and thus the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant enemy tooke off.</p>
            <p>Vpon this third let us ſtay our ſoules: I ſhall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with varietie of interpretations, nor with multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of obſervations which might very aptly be drawn out: but ſhall labour to preſent the ſumme in this generall inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Gods people may be in the burning, but they ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be reſcued and perfectly delivered.<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſhall labour to explaine and prove with the ſame labour.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Firſt, Here is implyed, that calamities by the enemy is a burning: as alſo, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.11. So this people finde it, and ſo expreſſe it, From above hath he ſent fire into my bones and it prevaileth againſt them: he hath burned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.13. Chap. 2.3.</note> like a flaming fire which devoureth round about.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 124.</note> If fire have the maſtery it is raging, devouring and waſting: fire and water have no mercy, we ſay of them, they are good ſervants, but ill maſters: ſo if the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell enemy get the maſtery he ruines all, and layes all waſte: A fire devoureth before them, and behind them a flame burneth;<note place="margin">Joel 2.3.</note> The land is as the garden of Eden before them, and behind them a deſolate wilderneſſe, yea and nothing ſhall eſcape them. When through the Lords anger this fire is kindled, it devoureth every greene tree with every dry tree, that is, both the good which are as the greene tree, having ſome ſap of grace, and the wicked which are as the dry tree, fit for nothing but fuell,<note place="margin">Ezek. 20.47.</note> and all faces from the North to the South ſhall be burnt therein: They pitie not the young, nor regard the perſon of the old: even as the devils malice and ſpite ceaſeth not, notwithſtanding, that <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and the Iews were but newly come out of the fire,<note place="margin">Auget culpam Satana. Drufius.</note> as it were brands halfe burnt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, burning is a tormenting, painfull puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112637:6"/>ſo is this: The Lord is angry and malicious men helpe forward the affliction: and it's more ſmarting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it's by their hand: when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous then he.<note place="margin">Hab. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, fire is unſatiable; it makes no end of burning ſo long as there is any thing combuſtible: Thus are the enemies, and the multitude of thoſe that diſtreſſe <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> they are even as a dream of a night viſion, as when a hungry man dreameth, and behold he eateth;<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.7, 8.</note> but he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waketh, and his ſoule is empty: or as when a thirſty man dreameth, and behold he drinketh; but he awaketh, and behold he is faint, and his ſoule hath appetite: although they load themſelves with plunder and ſpoyle, and glut and make themſelves drunk with bloud; yet they are no more ſatisfied then though they had onely dreamed of ſuch things: they are as one of the things that never ſay, <hi>It is enough:</hi> Their rage ends not with the life of the godly, but it extends it ſelfe even to their aſhes; as was ſeene in <hi>Wicklif, Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Phagius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Fire is purging: it trieth: it ſeparates, &amp; divides things Heterogeneall: as the droſſe from the ſilver: ſo this evill is to Gods people as a Refiners fire; it purgeth them from their hypocriſie, worldly-mindedneſſe, and ſelfe-love, &amp;c. Alſo it ſeparates the wicked of the earth as droſſe from the godly, as in this ſeaſon; the truly zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous from the malignant now combined together; <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> and his Angels, againſt the Dragon and his angels.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Secondly, here is implied,<note place="margin">Revel. 12.</note> that Gods people are often in this burning, and that to ſome extremitie, and for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, the Lord lets them lie in till they apprehend themſelves even conſumed as a brand in the fire.</p>
            <p>For firſt, we are not immediately purged, the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes are burnt, the lead is conſumed out of the fire,<note place="margin">Jerem. 6.</note> the Founder melts in vaine; the wicked nor our wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are not tooke away: as it is now ſeene, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are in the burning, yet our diſſentions and fires a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112637:7"/>our ſelves are not quenched; as it was with the <hi>Iewes</hi> when they were neere to be conſumed by the <hi>Romanes:</hi> our Pride, our Covetouſneſſe, &amp;c. are not tooke away; Then no wonder if we continue yet in the burning.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it may be alſo the Lord will thus feed the malignitie of the enemy, till he become prodigious in crueltie, blaſphemies, and inſolencie; and fill up a full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of vengeance for himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, Gods wiſdome is beſt ſeene when we are at our wits end; and the Lords power is moſt manifeſt, when we are at the extremitie of miſerie, when we think and ſay, we are cut off for our parts, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, when the enemies are at the height of their malice, and extremitie of crueltie: when the Pope was at his height, then <hi>Luther</hi> with others about that time gave him a ſecond deadly wound: and when Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this Nation groaned under the Hierarchie, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> under Egyptian Task-maſters; even then when Tyranny was come to the height, the Lord was ſeene in the Mount; then his wiſdome and power wrought for us: There was none to helpe, then his owne arme brought ſalvation by <hi>Englands</hi> Parliament, and <hi>Scotlands</hi> Armie: Thus ſome underſtand the enemies ruine, in <hi>Armageddon,</hi> expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be the Mount of <hi>Megiddo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 63.5. Revel. 16. Judg. 5.19.</note> becauſe the enemies are at a height when they are brought to <hi>Horma,</hi> an utter deſtruction, as <hi>Iſraels</hi> enemies were at the waters of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giddo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, contraries are ordinarily cured by contraries: cold diſeaſes by hot Medicines, and hot diſeaſes by cold: we are a cold Nation; at the moſt we are (as we are apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſembled by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Brightman</hi> to <hi>Laodicea</hi>) but luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme; therefore the Lord applies theſe burnings unto us, that he may bring ſome warmth into us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Thirdly, Here is expreſt, that though Gods people be in the fire, they ſhall certainly be pul'd out, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112637:7"/>out of <hi>Egypt</hi> from the Iron furnace, and out of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable captivitie in <hi>Babylon,</hi> where they indured this burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here mentioned: firſt, they are in hazard; then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly reſcued: <hi>The enemie ſaid, I will purſue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15.9, 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>I will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, I will divide the ſpoyle: my luſt ſhall bee ſatisfied on them: I will draw my ſword, mine hand ſhall deſtroy them. Thou didſt blow with thy wind, the Sea covered them: they ſanke as lead in the mighty waters.</hi> Then, Lord, <hi>thou in thy mercy haſt led forth the people whom thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So they ſeeme to be in their graves when in <hi>Babylon,</hi> but the Lord that quickneth the dead, tels them,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.19.</note> 
               <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live,</hi> the dead bodies ſhall ariſe: <hi>awake, and ſing ye that ſit in the duſt: for the Lords favour is as the dew of herbes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, thus the Lords Power, Wiſdome, and Truth ſhine forth when we ſay, Our bones are dried,<note place="margin">Ezek. 37.11.</note> and our hope is loſt; we are cut off for our parts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, then the Lord is ſought unto, (in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction they will ſeek me early) and reſted upon, when we know not what to doe; when refuge faileth, and none careth for our ſoules: And then the Lord will never leave us nor forſake us; he will not be as waters that faile.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Gods love is immutable; more conſtant then the mothers love to her ſucking child:<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.</note> No waters can quench it; the coales thereof are coales of fire which have a moſt vehement flame;<note place="margin">Cant. 8.</note> many waters cannot quench this love, &amp;c. In wrath he remembers mercy, and will not contend for ever, leſt the ſpirit ſhould faile before him,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.16.</note> and the ſoules that he hath made. The Lord will repent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for his ſervants, when he ſeeth that their power is gone; and there is none ſhut up, or left: <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teronomie</hi> 32.36. The tender mercies of the wicked are cruell, their malice is endleſſe; but the Lord in wrath remembers mercy: When his people are humbled, his repentings are kindled, his bowels are troubled, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112637:8"/>that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> hath received double at his hands for all their ſinnes.<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.2. <hi>Duplum in Chriſto.</hi> Junius.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo one addes an Argument beſides thoſe I have ſet downe out of theſe words, which may ſilence the Devill and all implacable enemies: Thus; <hi>This people is ſufficiently puniſht, therefore God is not to be urged to adde to their puniſhment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sanctius.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the enemy ſhall not alwaies blaſpheme; the Lord will ſtop the mouth of iniquitie, he will ſtill the enemy and avenger:<note place="margin">Deut. 32.26, 27.</note> the Lord would have ſcattered the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into corners, and cauſed the remembrance of them to ceaſe from among men, were it not that he feared the wrath of the enemy.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, thus the Lord takes courſe for his own Name; although not for our ſakes, yet for his owne Names ſake he will worke for us that his Name be not polluted. And ſo <hi>Ioſhua</hi> pleads,<note place="margin">Joſh. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. that for this reaſon the Lord would not leave his people in the enemies hand; for then, What (ſaith he) wilt thou doe unto thy glorious Name?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, here is implied; that if the Lord beginne in mercy he will finiſh:<note place="margin">Pſal. 102. Pſal. 138.8.</note> when the time to favour <hi>Sion,</hi> the ſet time is come, then the Lord will perfect his worke concerning us: he will doe it in deſpight of all Devils and Antichriſtians: though there be mountaines before his <hi>Zerubbabels,</hi> God will make them plaines, and bring forth the head-ſtone of his worke with ſhouting: He can make the hardeſt reſiſtance as Clay, or Wax to the Signet; the greateſt impediment ſhall give place, as <hi>Euphrates</hi> did to <hi>Cyrus</hi> that he might take the old <hi>Babylon;</hi> He ſaith to the deepe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.</note> Be drie: and ſo will the Lord doe that he may be avenged on <hi>Rome, Revel.</hi> 16.11.</p>
            <p>Yea, things adverſe ſhall not onely yeeld, but concurre: The Lord will make away in the wilderneſſe, and rivers in the deſert; the beaſts of the field ſhall honour him, the Dragon,<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.19, 20, 21.</note> and the Owles, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As the beginnings of the ruine of the wicked eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112637:8"/>their certaine totall ruine: If <hi>Haman</hi> begin to fall, he ſhall not faile but fall: ſo the beginnings of deliverance from our Romiſh enemies, are pledges of compleat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; the beginnings of the repairing of Gods Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, evidence the certaine finiſhing of it: beginnings of woe were ſignes to the <hi>Iews</hi> of the extremitie of woe: and beginnings of bleſſedneſſe and puritie, are like ſignes of perfect bleſſedneſſe and puritie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the Lord hath choſen <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings declare what he hath decreed: If God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to deliver, to build, to beautifie the place of his Foot-ſtoole and make it glorious, who can hinder? the Lord God hath purpoſed, and who can diſanull it?<note place="margin">Iſa. 14.24.27.</note> he hath ſtretched forth his hand, and who can turne it back?</p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſtands God upon for his honour to goe on in mercy, when he begins in mercy: his Truth, his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and Power are ingaged: <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore was much affected when the Lord threatened to deſtroy <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> as one man, after he had puld them out of the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an burnings:<note place="margin">Exod. 32.12.</note> Lord (ſaith he) why doth thy wrath waxe hot againſt thy people, which thou haſt brought forth out of the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> with great power, and with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand? Wherefore ſhould the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſpeake and ſay, for miſchiefe did he bring them out to ſlay them in the mountaines?<note place="margin">Num. 14.15, 16.</note> And now if thou wilt kill all this people as one man, then the Nations which have heard the fame of thee will ſpeake, ſaying: Becauſe the Lord was not able to bring this people into <hi>Canaan,</hi> he hath ſlaine them in the wilderneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Lord would not have us ſuch unwiſe builders as beginne and cannot finiſh; ſuch builders are expoſed to ſcorne and ſhame; therefore the omnipotent onely wiſe God will not doe ſo.</p>
            <p>The Lord alſo is tender of his ſervants honour: he will ſtill the enemie, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. <hi>Sanballat, Tobiah,</hi> and <hi>Geſhem</hi> will laugh <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and other Worthies to ſcorne:<note place="margin">Neh. 2.19, 20.</note> What
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112637:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112637:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112637:10"/>is this thing that ye doe?<note place="margin">Neh. 4.2, 3, 4.</note> Will ye rebell againſt the King? What doe theſe feeble <hi>Iewes?</hi> will they fortifie? will they ſacrifice? Then his fellow: Even that which they build, if a Foxe goe up he will breake down their ſtone wall: but <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and ſuch, may be confident and ſay, The God of heaven will proſper us, therefore we his ſervants will ariſe and build; and make all knowne to God who careth for your perſons, your names, and honours: Heare, O our God, for we are deſpiſed, and turne their reproach upon their owne head. The reproach of his ſervants he will wipe away:<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.5.</note> The Lord will appeare to your joy when they ſhall be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God is conſtant: ſo is his love and reſolution to doe us good: he is not as the ſonne of man that he ſhould repent:<note place="margin">Num. 23.19. Mal. 3.6. 1 Sam. 12.22.</note> he is God and changeth not: The Lord will not forſake his people for his great Names ſake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord to make you his people: Therefore when the Lord beginnes he goeth on: as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omi</hi> ſaid of <hi>Booz,</hi> The man will not be in reſt untill he finiſh the things this day. Men are mutable, diſcouraged, weary; but the Creator of the ends of the earth fainteth not: <hi>Natura not dilaſſatur opere;</hi> as the heavens are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wearie; the Sunne after millions of revolutions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth ſtill rejoycing as a mighty man to runne his race; much leſſe is the God of Nature, and the God of theſe Heavens weary: ſhall the Lord then begin and not finiſh? Shall I bring to the birth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.9.</note> and not cauſe to bring forth, ſaith the Lord? The Lords care over his Church, is alſo a conſtant care; his eyes are continually upon it: upon one ſtone, that is, Chriſt Ieſus, the Corner-ſtone on whom we are built: there are ſeven eyes; that is, many eyes; the Lords eyes are upon Gods Houſe,<note place="margin">Populi cauſam Deus ſemel tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cudan ſuſcepit, ac proinde qua eſt conſtantia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nquam deſeret cam. <hi>Druſius.</hi>
               </note> his choſen, and ſo ſhall be till all be perfected concerning his people. They may be in the burning, but they ſhall certainly be reſcued: and if ſo, perfectly delivered: The conſtant zeale of the Lord of Hoſts will performe this</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:112637:10"/>
Firſt, ſympathize and pity <hi>Ireland</hi> almoſt burnt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Levit. 10.6.</note> and <hi>England</hi> in the fire. Let the whole houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> bewaile the burning which the Lord hath kindled: let your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions be toward the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> that Vine that had ſtrong rods for the Scepters of them that beare rule: but fire is gone out of a rod of her branches which hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured her fruit,<note place="margin">Ezek. 19. ult.</note> ſo that there is no rod for a Scepter to rule. This is a lamentation, and it ſhall be for a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: let your compaſſions be kindled ſo that they may ſet you on a courſe to help them out of the fire: uſe means (as the Lord hath put into your hands) if ſo be there may be balme for their healing: if we ſhall ſtill look on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contributing to their reliefe, looke for the like meaſure from others in our miſeries: Who ſhall pity thee, O <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> or who ſhall bemoane thee? or who will turn aſide to aske how thou doſt? we have beene too much and too long wanting unto Gods diſtreſſed Churches; feare leſt the fire of Gods anger be kindled againſt us, becauſe we have beene a ſtaffe of reed unto the houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 29.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, let the Lord be magnified by us. Firſt, for giving warning: he ſets us on fire round about, before his wrath kindle upon us. It is the Lords mercies that we are not conſumed: let your praiſe be continually of him for keeping off this fire: when the enemy hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in like a floud, the Spirit of the Lord hath lift up a Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard againſt him: he hath appointed barres and limits unto theſe raging waves of the enemy, and ſaid, Stay there thy proud waves and goe no further.</p>
            <p>Secondly, bleſſe the Lord for chaſtiſing in meaſure, for that he hath not powred out all his anger; he might have ſcattered Brimſtone upon our habitations, and made us as <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſe our God ye people, &amp;c. For thou O God, haſt proved us, thou haſt tried us as ſilver is tried;<note place="margin">Pſa. 66.</note> we went through fire and through water; hence we have good hone that the Lord hath not ordained us to wrath: for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112637:11"/>when we are judged we are chaſtened of the Lord, that we ſhould not be condemned with the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, magnifie the Lords Omnipotencie, that hath kept his Church in the midſt of flames.<note place="margin">Numb. 21.</note> The buſh burneth and is not conſumed: <hi>Iſrael</hi> was preſerved among fiery Serpents; ſo are we kept amongſt a Malignant company (the brood of the Serpent) who are ſet on fire: Magnifie the God of Truth who hath ſpoke with his mouth, and with his hand fulfilled it: When thou walkeſt through the fire,<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.2.</note> thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</p>
            <p>Is it not marvellous in your eyes that the religious in <hi>France</hi> have beene preſerved in Maſſacres and Butcheries, and the Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> in the fires in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> reigne; and ſince from the damnable Powder-Plot; and many a time ſince from the Antichriſtians ſet on fire againſt us, and their Adherents, brutiſh men, skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to deſtroy?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, let the Lord be magnified for making ſome impreſſions on the Antichriſtian party: The Lord God of recompences hath begun to give burning for burning. Let all give glory to the Lord for ſtirring up the ſpirits of our Worthies to hate the Whore, to make her deſolate, to eat her fleſh, and burne her with fire: O glorifie ye the Lord in the midſt of the fires.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let us not think our ſelves exempt: the Lord hath brought this fire upon all his people, and ſhall we be free?</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore ſhake off ſecuritie, and beſtirre your ſelves to prevent and keepe our ſelves out; we have been as brands in the fire; The burnt child dreads the fire. Our neighbours houſe is on fire, we cannot but be concerned in this. I will not meddle in Politiques, onely adviſe thus. Therefore, firſt, kindle not the Lords jealouſie by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions; caſt not a favourable eye toward the Whore of <hi>Rome;</hi> leave not an hoofe of the Beaſt in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112637:11"/>
Secondly, tempt not God: complaine not of his wiſe adminiſtration: thinke not, ſay not as <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Can God doe this? can he perfect Reformation? can he give pure Ordinances? can he ſubdue ſuch a people as we are to his Scepter? can he ordaine Peace? can he worke all our workes for us? When the Lord heard this he was wroth, ſo a fire was kindled againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.21.</note> and anger alſo came up againſt <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, purge out every curſed ſinne by repentance: let this be manifeſted in a holy indignation againſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of Idolatry and Superſtition, as you have zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly begun: make the ſtones of the Altars as Chalke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, beat them to pieces:<note place="margin">Iſa. 27.</note> Every ſinne makes us as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to take fire, even as Gun-powder: let us therefore have grace whereby we may ſerve God acceptably with reverence and godly feare: for firſt, Our God is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire: and ſecondly, this fire of the Enemy is dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: A fire devoureth before them, and behinde them a flame burneth: all that is deſireable will be conſumed by them: Gods Sanctuary ſhall be laid waſte, his Worſhip, his Ordinances polluted, we ſhall loſe communion of Saints, the excellencie of our ſtrength, the deſire of our eyes; no fire makes ſuch a deſolation as this: An Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Army is the abomination of deſolation.<note place="margin">Ezek. 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And if the Lord have ſtretched out his hand ſo that we cannot put it back but that this fire doe kindle upon us, I ſhall preſcribe the ſame courſe; Turn to him that ſmiteth: take away the ſting from the fiery Serpents: that is, our ſinnes: The ſting of death and every deadly evill is ſinne: ſinne is as fuel and bellowes, both increaſing the flame, and the wrath of God as a ſtreame of Brimſtone: If we could have broken hearts, the Lord would binde up our broken State, our broken Church. If we be not found in our ſins, the fire can have no power over us:<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> Satan ſhall not be at our right hand ſo as to prevaile. But if we continue in our neutralitie, like warmeneſſe, diviſions and heats one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112637:12"/>another, in covetouſneſſe, pride, injuſtice, unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, deſpiſing the day of ſmall things, and contempt of the Goſpel, grieving Gods holy Spirit, by which he ſtill ſtriveth with us; the Lord wil be turned to he our enemie: how then can our hearts endure, or our hands be ſtrong in the day that the Lord ſhall deale with us? hereunto will be added the burning of an evill conſcience,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.</note> a terrible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire: and thus the fire will be as <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> furnace,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> ſeven times hotter.</p>
            <p>Be inſtructed leſt the Lords ſoule depart from you; let this fire that the Lord hath kindled be a Refiners fire, leſt the Lord come from his place as a conſuming fire, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting burnings.</p>
            <p>Our God hath beene trying to purge us a long time, he hath ſmitten us with Peſtilence after the manner of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but we have not turned to him; he hath now drawne out his ſword to avenge the quarrell of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the fire of his anger burnes; but he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine as of old,<note place="margin">Jer. 6.</note> The Founder melts in vaine; our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is not tooke away by repentance, the wicked are not tooke away by the hand of juſtice: Or as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.18. The houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is become droſſe: all they are braſſe, and iron, and tinne, and lead, in the midſt of the furnace; they are even the droſſe of ſilver.</p>
            <p>Behold therefore, (O tremble at this) I will gather you into the midſt of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in mine anger, and in my fury, and I will leave you there and melt you; yea I will gather you and blow upon you in the fire of my wrath, &amp;c. and ye ſhall know that I the Lord have powred out my fury upon you. O then heare the rod and who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it: it is an ill ſigne when we are ſet on fire round about and lay it not to heart: An ill ſigne when we are with the old World and <hi>Sodome</hi> ſecure; when we put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the evill day, and think when the overflowing ſcourge paſſeth through the Citie it ſhall not come neere us. This Citie is the Cauldron, and we are the fleſh; and when we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112637:12"/>make the Lord complaine, as <hi>Amos</hi> 4.11. Ye were as a firebrand pluckt out of the burning; yet ye have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to me: and when unfruitfull, notwithſtanding Sunne and raine, like that curſed earth: our end is to be burned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when we are in the burning look up to Ieſus Chriſt, (as the Iſraelites being bit with fiery Serpents lookt up to the brazen Serpent) thus we ſhall have heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">Num. 11.3.</note> by faith we may quench the violence of flames.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> In Chriſt we ſhall have ſafetie. This man ſhall be the peace when the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> (the greateſt enemy that ever <hi>Iſrael</hi> had) cometh into the Land.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, labour for the Spirit of comfort; The refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Spirit, as living water, will coole the heat of the ſpent ſoule.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, pray that the Lord would mitigate the flames: ſo he did for thoſe three, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. and for ſome Martyrs: pray and draw out water as in buckets, and powre it out before the Lord: It will be a ſure meanes of quenching: when <hi>Moſes</hi> prayed, the burning at <hi>Tabera</hi> was quenched.</p>
            <p>Labour to be conſtant; hold faſt the Name of Chriſt: the Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> is a patterne to us: that held faſt and denied not the faith when <hi>Antipas</hi> ſuffered martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and where Satan dwelled: doe likewiſe:<note place="margin">Revel. 3.</note> you have covenanted with God: deale not falſly in his Covenant: let not your ſteps decline out of the way though the Lord ſhould ſmite you into the place of Dragons,<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.</note> and cover you with the ſhadow of death: for your encouragement hearken to the Lord of Hoſts, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.7. If you will walke in my wayes, and keep my charge, then you ſhall alſo judge my houſe, and keepe my Courts, and I will give thee places to walke among them that ſtand by. (Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Worthies) if you will perſevere zealouſly in the Lords worke, you ſhall be advanced to be among Angels: though you cannot have the preſence and face of an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112637:13"/>King, you ſhall be with the glorious Angels ſtanding before the face of the King of heaven.</p>
            <p>This may be abundant comfort unto you (much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured) and to all Gods people:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4.</note> We are in the fire but firſt, the Lord is with you and all his,<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.2.</note> ſo that the flame ſhall not devoure.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you are choyce Inſtruments, Gods people are his choſen; choice gold will endure the fire, and the Lord will not caſt away his people whom he hath choſen: when the houſe is on fire we take care for our Treaſure; our choyce veſſels, our jewels: we are not ſo ſolicitous for lumber: ſo the Lord careth for you and all his; you are his choyce Veſſels,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> and peculiar Treaſure, and his Iewels very precious in the Lords eyes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt the Sonne of God intercedes for you, and that affectionately; he will prevaile with God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the Adverſarie: and that to the purpoſe. The Lord rebuke thee,<note place="margin">Increpationem tuam contra te dirigat. <hi>Dion. Carthul.</hi>
               </note> the Lord rebuke thee: even as Chriſt rebuked Windes and Seas; ſo will he doe with Satan and all his inſtruments: as <hi>Nahum.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, let the gracious beginning which the Lord hath made be a ſure pledge unto you that he will finiſh: be bold to plead with God: Lord thou wouldeſt not that we ſhould undertake a building and not finiſh it, thou haſt undertaken to build thy Houſe here, be not ſo thy ſelfe as thou wouldeſt not that we ſhould be.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the Lord hath promiſed great things, and ſpoke of glorious dayes which now haſten concerning his Church: nothing ſhall hurt in Gods holy Mountaine. The earth ſhall be filled with the knowledge of the glory of the Lord as the waters cover the Sea:<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.</note> the waſte and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late places, and the land of thy deſtruction ſhall be too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row by reaſon of the Inhabitants; and they that ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee up ſhall be farre away.<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.18.</note> O thou afflicted and toſſed with tempeſt, and not comforted; behold, I will lay thy ſtones with faire colours, and thy foundation with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phires;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112637:13"/>and I will make thy windowes of Agats,<note place="margin">Iſa. 54.11, 12.</note> and thy gates of Carbuncles, &amp;c. And all thy children ſhall be taught of the Lord; and great ſhall be the peace of thy children. The time and my ſtrength would faile to recite the glorious things that are ſpoken of thee, thou Citie of God, the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> coming downe from heaven with Gods glory upon her: In that day, ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Zach. 12.</note> I will make the Governours of <hi>Iuda</hi> as an hearth of fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the wood; and like a torch of fire in a ſheafe: and they that have fought againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> their fleſh ſhall conſume away whileſt they ſtand upon their feet;<note place="margin">Zach. 14.</note> and their eies ſhall conſume away in their holes, &amp;c. Thus (Right Honourable) be comforted over the Church of God now in the burning; and over your enemies which are ordained for deſtruction, by the words of the God of Truth. The Lord bids them take away <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> filthy rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and reſtore to the Prieſthood its former luſtre, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by change of raiment: Hence ſaith Maſter <hi>Calvin: Plus expectent fideles quam coniicere licet ex praeſenti aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu:</hi> Expect more then the preſent face of things can promiſe: the Lord will be known to be <hi>Iehovah</hi> in giving a being to his Word; He will be with you, feare not:<note place="margin">Hag. 2.5. Pſal. 68.13.</note> Though ye have beene among the pots, yet ſhall ye be as a Dove coverd with ſilver, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Therefore let every man in his Sphere be incouraged to be active and zealous to forward and haſten the perfect deliverance of Gods Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5.</note> and the perfect building and furniſhing of Gods Houſe: be not ſcandalized, be not diſheartened for every dyſaſter, or for any preſent weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or miſerie we are in; the Lord carrieth on the worke of reſtitution and ſalvation of his Church and people in a myſterie: when we are at the top of miſery, the Lord will be ſeene, <hi>Iehovah iireth:</hi> the Lord will be ſeene, or will ſee: even in the Mount his footſteps are hardly knowne: the Sunne ariſeth and ſhineth upon <hi>Sodome,</hi> then the Lord rained fire and brimſtone from the Lord out of heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:112637:14"/>Gods people lie as buried or burnt up in <hi>Babylon,</hi> then the Lord ſends from heaven and ſaveth them from thoſe that would ſwallow them up: This is the ſeaſon not for ſhrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but for zeale;<note place="margin">1 Chron. 14.</note> the Lord hath gone out before you, and broke in upon the enemies as the breaking in of many waters; therefore now beſtirre you: Thoſe of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> are commended becauſe they had knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Times,<note place="margin">1 Chro. 12.32.</note> and knew what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to doe: This will be your wiſdome to take notice that to hazard that Chriſts kingdome is in by Enemies abroad, and Schiſmes and Diviſions among our ſelves in this ſeaſon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires all your diligence, skill, and power to bring preſent healing and aide. And ſo now when <hi>Babylons</hi> rage &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie is at the height, it is the time, it is the time to render to her double as ſhe hath done to you. In this ſeaſon we are in ſtraits, as when the children are come to the birth and there is no ſtrength to bring forth: Is it not time for us then to ſtirre in theſe ſtraits; ſtrive, and extend your ſelves to get Gods children, and the Lords worke drawne out of the wombe: let not that be your ſpot which was the ſpot of <hi>Ephraim</hi> in the like caſe; the ſorrowes of a travelling woman are upon him: He is an unwiſe ſonne, for he ſhould not ſtay long in the place of the breaking forth of children.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now we are in the fire, let your zeale hence be enkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: take fire from this fire: Every man, eſpecially Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, Repairers, Deliverers muſt be ſalted with fire, as every ſacrifice was ſeaſoned with ſalt;<note place="margin">Mar. 9.</note> be ye therefore thus ſeaſoned with this heavenly fire of zeale, without which all will be unſavorie, that you may goe on in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the great workes you have in hand. Further to provoke you, I adde ſome further incentives.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Obſerve that the builders and reformers had as many diſcouragements as are now; they had a great worke before them, many enemies about them, and the Kings Authoritie and expreſſe command againſt them;<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:112637:14"/>yet they went on and proſpered; there were Mountains before them,<note place="margin">Zach. 4.7, 8, 9.</note> but God made all plaine in a ſtrange way of providence; Not by Army nor Power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord: He will doe the like for you. Onely, as it is ſaid to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> Be of good courage: The Lord can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the Devil and all his Inſtruments with a word, and make them as ſtill as a ſtone.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If ye faint and grow cold, ye loſe all that hath gone before: (ye Worthies) ye have done much in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe Poperie, a Tyrannous Hierarchie, and the ſtrength of <hi>Babylons</hi> Armies; ye have begun a glorious Reformation, and your Zeale hath ſet you upon high un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, and effected ſuch things as we, through our baſeneſſe of ſpirit, neither looked not hoped for: you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered as much as did ever any Parliament; hazarding your Perſons, Eſtates, and Families; indured much contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſinners, and many reproaches; ye have had many acknowledgements and thankeſgivings from Citie and Countrey. O then loſe not all that hath gone before; let your laſt be more then the firſt: Will ye do, will ye ſuffer ſo many things in vaine?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Ye worke with God, and the Lord will work with you; It is an honour to the nobleſt to put their necks to this worke: The Sonne of God appeareth upon a Red Horſe, going out in a fiery appearance againſt the enemie: He is among the Myrtle trees; that is, in the midſt of his people, who are his delight; and with him there are Red Horſes alſo: <hi>Michael</hi> hath his Angels to take vengeance on the Dragon and his angels: alſo there are ſpeckled Horſes, uſefull every way, both for defence and offence.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The great oppoſitions you have ſhould ſtirre up zeale; the god of the world is againſt you; Antichriſt, and all that have the marke of the Beaſt upon them, are againſt you: You are ingaged in the greateſt worke that ever lay upon the children of men; therefore there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſtrong endeavours. O be ſtrong, ye <hi>Zerubbabels,</hi> he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112637:15"/>for the Lord of Hoſts who hath beene zealous for you: and withall take notice that your oppoſition is from deviliſh and malignant ſpirits; Satan and his Inſtruments who ſtand at your right hands to reſiſt: Then up and be doing; goe on, your cauſe cannot but be good.</p>
            <p>Firfthly, Take courage and goe on, elſe ye open the mouth of iniquitie; you will be tried with cruel mockings by thoſe that looke and gape to ſee your ſpirits flat and cold: Oh how will they of <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askelon</hi> inſult? this will pierce as a ſword; <hi>Saul</hi> choſe rather to fall on his owne ſword and die, then to be mocked by the uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed <hi>Philiſtines:</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah</hi> would not yeeld, (but let come on him whatſoever it was) becauſe he feared to be ſcorned and mocked: And conſider, I beſeech you, that we have made out boaſt of God, and gloried in ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; let not our confident boaſting make us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Thus if you goe on, you and we may leave hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to our poſteritie: if through our ſlackneſſe and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimitie the enemie prevaile, we ſhall have nothing left to bequeath but Slavery and Popery.</p>
            <p>Sevently, Antichriſts end is neere: <hi>Babylon</hi> is (and that ſhortly) to be deſtroyed, therefore faint not: you have given her a deadly wound, follow on your ſtroke; let that wound never be healed: the Beaſt roares, and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, and beſtirres her ſelfe; ſhe recollects ſpirits, but it is but as in a dying man, <hi>naturea ultimus conatus,</hi> which we call a lightening before death: then now is the time to extend your ſelves to make a full end of the Whore; to diſpatch her with ſwords (as the Prophet ſpeakes) and to burne her houſes with fire.</p>
            <p>Then keepe your ſpirits up, fall not to an indifferencie or baſe neutrality: They that be not with Chriſt are againſt him: They that come not out to the help of the Lord, (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they be inoffenſive moderate men) are curſed with a double bitter curſe.<note place="margin">Judg. 5.</note> The hiſtory of the men of <hi>Iabeſh Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:112637:15"/>may be for our learning on whom theſe ſad times are come: They aſſiſted not the <hi>Beniamites</hi> in protecting thoſe Delinquents, ſonnes of <hi>Belial;</hi> nor aſſociated with the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their juſt Warre, which was (as this Warre now) to bring ſuch wretches to judgement and puniſhment. Vpon inquiry theſe being found Neuters, were dealt withall as utter enemies; they were all ſmitten with the ſword, both men, women and children,<note place="margin">Judg. cap. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> except ſome virgins reſerved for the <hi>Beniamites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech you that my exhortation and adviſe may be acceptable: I could multiply many other conſiderations to ſet you on in a courſe of zeale; but if theſe I have ſpoke helpe not to bring you to a further degree of heate, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally now that we are in the fire round about; we may feare that gray haires are upon us, we are in a decaying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as <hi>David,</hi> whom many cloathes could not make warme.</p>
            <p>Let all malignant ſpirits marke:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 6.</note> let this conſideration take them off from their malice in oppoſing. <hi>Altaſchith</hi> is the title of ſome Pſalmes: Deſtroy not, as a caution and a confident expreſſion of the boldneſſe, malice, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of the enemie. Let the gold and ſilver veſſels, &amp;c. be every one in his place, as it is by <hi>Darius</hi> Decree ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Cyrus:</hi> Now therefore <hi>Tatnai</hi> and <hi>Shethar-Boznai,</hi> and ſo <hi>Rehum</hi> the Chancellour, and <hi>Shimſhai</hi> the Scribe and ſuch companions muſt be farre from thence.</p>
            <p>If thou oppoſe the peace of Gods people, and the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lords houſe, it is in vaine; thou wilt be found to fight againſt God; It is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks: therefore meddle not to thy hurt; the Lord will finiſh in deſpight of thee: The Devil and his inſtruments could doe nothing when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in <hi>Chaldea</hi> depreſt and buried; how much leſſe now when they are delivered, lift up to Heaven, brought to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and the Temple? ſo the policie and power of the enemy could doe nothing when the faithfull were enthralled under the Hierarchie,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112637:16"/>when they had all advantages: how much leſſe now, when the Lord hath tooke off thoſe yokes, and advanced his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants as the ſtarres into the right hand of Chriſt? <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>But the Devils malice is ſuch, that although he know that his owne practiſes ſhall ruine his owne kingdome, yet he will not, he cannot deſiſt from miſchiefe: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice is naturall to the Devil, and therefore he is neceſſarily malicious, as the fire is naturally and ſo neceſſarily hot and burning:<note place="margin">Zanch. de malis angelis.</note> and as <hi>Zanch.</hi> ſaith, <hi>id in angelis eſt caſus quod hominibus mors:</hi> therefore as men after death are either pertinaciouſly evill, or conſtantly good; ſo are the Devils after their fall pertinaciouſly wicked and malicious: and ſo it is with Gods enemies in whom the devil workes with efficacie: they are not onely deviliſh, but even equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the devill in malice and miſchiefe; <hi>Iudas</hi> was even a devil, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>The enemies know and ſee that the Lord is with his Parliament, with his Armies, yet they go on; the devil drives them and thruſts them on as the Turkiſh horſemen doe their foot to their manifeſt inevitable ruine. When thy hand is lifted up,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.11.</note> they will not ſee. It is an evidence of and dealings, as <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. It is noted that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the powring out of the vials they were vexed and pained, and gnawed their tongues; yet they repented not: <hi>and they repented not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O let this take thee off, when the Lords hand is lifted upon to deliver his people, or judge the enemies: Thou wilt not ſee, but thou ſhalt ſee to thy woe, if thou goeſt on to oppoſe the Lord. It is uſually askt: Is the devill in ſuch a one whom we ſee mad and maliciouſly bent? what devil then ſhall we thinke is in thoſe that will yet in malignitie of ſpirit oppoſe themſelves?<note n="*" place="margin">Qua voce adeo potenter fregit ſatanae vires, ut nullum poſtea reliquum fuerit impedimentum. <hi>Zanch. in loc.</hi>
               </note> This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion for ought we know took off the devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as thus: doeſt thou not ſee that the Lord hath puld his people out of the fire? he thinks they have burnt long
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112637:16"/>enough; he hath begun their deliverance, and ſo is ingaged to perfect it: then why wilt thou offer to be an adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary? how tranſcendently deviliſh then are thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of all pietie? they ſee that there is no wiſdome, nor underſtanding, nor counſell againſt the Lord; and yet they will continue obſtinate in their malice. The Lord rebuke them, the Lord that hath choſen <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> rebuke them:<note place="margin">Job 41.8.</note> O conſider, ye that forget God, whom you have to deale withall: Remember the Battle and doe no more.</p>
            <p>I adde to this an admonition to every one.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 7.</note> O let us take heed of hindering the good of Chriſts Church and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: Know I beſeech you, that it is not onely hindered by Malignitie and Neutralitie: but even the beſt have a hand in ſtopping God, which cauſeth him after he hath begun ſo to pauſe and to be at a ſtand: How?</p>
            <p>Firſt, by our Infidelitie: Thus were <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and all Iſrael kept out of Canaan after their deliverance out of Egypt:<note place="margin">Matth. 13. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> The Lord cannot do many moe mightie works for us, becauſe of our unbeliefe; Thus when things are adverſe, we give our ſelves for loſt, our hope is cut off, as though God were not all-ſufficient: when things are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous we do nothing leſſe then reſt on God, we leane on an arme of fleſh, we have a prudent Parliament, a potent Army, we have counſell and ſtrength for warre: ſo the Lord is depreſt and theſe exalted, which provokes the Lord to let us ſee the vanitie of theſe without his helping band, and may provoke him to reject our confidences and ſweare in his wrath that we ſhould never proſper in them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there hath been but bad uſe made of Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings. Firſt, we have deſpiſed the day of ſmall things: Thankfulneſſe would make us account ſmall beginnings great favours: yet what the Lord hath already wrought ſhould not ſeeme ſmall in our eyes: conſidering what the Lord hath pull'd down, and what he is ſetting up, what he hath pluckt up, and what he is about to plant, what task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters we are delivered from, and what bleſſed freedome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112637:17"/>we enjoy. Succeſſes have made us more inſulting then thankfull, and tooke us off from our dependance on God who wrought for us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are a ſtubborn people; now that Chriſt would reigne amongſt us, we ſay this man ſhall not reigne over us: now Chriſt is coming toward us, we bid him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of our coaſts: we are loath to ſubject our necks to his yoke, our pride is ſuch: This makes him alſo at a ſtand.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſince the Lord hath multiplyed mercies, we have multiplyed diviſions, and keepe in and foment ſuch fires of diſſention among our ſelves, as juſtly provokes the Lord to let us lye in the burning: Such a fire was kindled between <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and the men of <hi>Shechem,</hi> fire went out from <hi>Sechem</hi> and devoured <hi>Abimelech;</hi> and fire went out from <hi>Abimelech</hi> &amp; devoured the men of <hi>Shechem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 9.</note> the Lord quench the fire threatening the like evils amongſt us: It is a fearefull ſigne of the fire of Gods anger ready to kindle on us when he ſends and ſuffers an evill ſpirit to prevaile ſo between King and people; but for the diviſions of Gods people there ſhould be great thoughts of heart; as for the diviſions of <hi>Reuben</hi> there were great thoughts, and great ſeachings of heart. It is to be lamented with the teares of us all, to ſee brethren agreeing in all ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials; ſerving one God, having one Father and Hope, &amp;c. yet for ſome circumſtances in matters of Diſcipline their contentions are as the barres of a Caſtle, and the heat is increaſed, as betweene <hi>Guelphs</hi> and <hi>Gibellines.</hi> Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Senators, here your Wiſdome (yea a Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from above muſt be obtained for you) would ſhine if you could repaire all theſe breaches, and compoſe things ſo, that brethren might with peace of conſcience dwell together in unitie, then we ſhould ſee that the Lord would delight over us to goe on to doe great things for us: and the graces of God would then ſhine in his ſervants when they would in the ſpirit of meekneſſe yeeld one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112637:17"/>ſo that the unitie of the ſpirit might be kept in the bond of peace: This onely I adde; If ye bite and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure one another,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> take heed that ye be not conſumed one of another.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when we have had mercies ſhowring down from heaven, we have ſlackt our hands in prayer: when <hi>Moſes</hi> hands fell downe, <hi>Amalek</hi> prevailed; and ſo through our ſlacknes &amp; coldneſſe in this dutie and others, more then through the ſlackneſſe of our Armies; the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies who were not long ſince even prayed downe, have ſtrengthened themſelves to our reproach and danger.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Selfe-love, which ſets us upon ſelfe-ſeeking, and ſelfe-ends, is ſo predominant, that the publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments are not ſo promoted: If we had publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments are not ſo promoted: If we had publique ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, our endevours would have had a further influence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the publique good then yet they have had.</p>
            <p>And many provocations there are amongſt us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile; many <hi>Achans</hi> amongſt us, many curſed things, not onely hid in the tents; but brought forth in the ſight of the Sunne; they declare their ſinne as <hi>Sodome,</hi> and hide it not: much cauſe of humiliation theſe are unto us all this day: and we muſt not looke to ſee Gods work-perfected till we All mourne and repent for the many evils in the midſt of us: How long ſhall I ſee the Standard, and heare the ſound of the Trumpet?<note place="margin">Jer. 4.21.</note> It is anſwered in the next words by the Prophet; My people is fooliſh, &amp;c. <hi>Junius</hi> reads it, <hi>So long as my people is fooliſh and ſottiſh, and wiſe to doe evill.</hi> And (Honoured Worthies) I beſeech you to admit of me that I may uſe boldneſſe: This burden con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns all, and cals upon all; it is for admonition to all, but eſpecially You: When <hi>Iſrael</hi> had provoked the Lord by their ſpell and bodily uncleaneſſe, the people were plagued in a fearefull manner; there fell in one day foure and twenty thouſand: <hi>Moſes</hi> was not blamed,<note place="margin">Num. 25.</note> but the Heads of the people: Hang up the heads of the people that the fierce anger of the Lord may be turned away from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112637:18"/>
               <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Why the Heads of the people? They ſhould have lookt better to the people in governing, ſo to prevent ſin; or they ſhould have beene more ſwift to execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they fell into ſinne: It is not enough that you are not groſſe ſinners, that you are reformed, ſo long as there are in the midſt of Citie and Kingdome, even where your Power alſo reacheth, many abominations; there are as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.</note> in thee; in thee much exceſs, many profanations, horrible uncleanneſſe, (I ſpeake what I know) even abominable inceſt, not onely acted once or twice, but continued in to the juſt provocation of Gods anger againſt you and all of us; and there is no courſe for redreſſe, none to puniſh or put them to ſhame: there is in the midſt of us oppreſſion and crueltie, there are in the midſt of us many Innocents whoſe faces are ground, and their bones cruſht and broken moſt injuriouſly; they cry for reliefe, they ſtretch out their hands to you for helpe: O releeve the oppreſſed, and judge the cauſe of the help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, leſt the Lord heare their cry and it be ſinne unto you.</p>
            <p>Delay not, make ſpeed to ſeeke judgement, to bring the wheele upon the wicked; put not off ſuch things; the delaying of which, delayes all your hopefull proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: delay not one day to trouble thoſe that trouble <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:</hi> but as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſaid, ſo doe ye; God ſhall trouble thee this day. Theſe and many ſuch things lye upon you: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore provoke your ſpirits to zeale and courage; feare not, faint not; if Chriſt had fainted in the worke of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, what had become of us? he fainted not, not was diſcouraged till he ſet judgement in the Earth; do ye likewiſe.</p>
            <p>Obſerve how the Lord deſcribeth the Horſe, <hi>Iob</hi> 39. His neck is cloathed with thunder, he paweth in the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and rejoyceth in his ſtrength; he goeth out to meet the armed man, the quiver rattleth at him, the glittering ſpeare and the ſhield; he ſaith among the Trumpets, aha! and doth God care for horſes? glorifie God in the creature
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112637:18"/>and learne courage from him; break through all like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: as in naturall motion, ſo the neerer you come to your haven where you would be, let your motion be ſwifter: The Lords beginnings engage him to finiſh; ye are Gods, as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 82. Follow God: the Lord hath beene very zealous for you and us, take heed of coldneſſe in this heat: labour to haſten Reformation in the Church, that it may be the gladneſſe of Gods people to goe to the beautie of holineſſe, that the Tribes may goe up to the Teſtimony of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and for the better governing the Common-wealth, let there be ſet thrones of judgement in all places: as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.</p>
            <p>And to conclude: Let us all put to our helping hands, armes, purſes, counſell, encouragement, for the helpe of the Lord againſt the mightie: let the Miniſters of Chriſt be carefull to maintaine unitie; to provoke Chriſtians to peace; to unite againſt the common Enemie: on ſome have compaſſion, making a difference; and others ſave with terrour, pulling them out of the fire. O let all be humbled before our God this day, and put our mouthes in the duſt; and then our prayers will be very prevalent with God; our legions would be thundering legions, as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian armies of old, dreadfull to the enemie: let us all helpe with our conſtant prayers, be the Lords remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers, give him no reſt till he refine his Church, and pull it out of the fire: he that hath neither purſe, nor wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, nor hands, nor counſell to helpe, hath a heart; O poure it out in prayer; give not over till the Lord hath made <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the earth. It is uſuall to put words into a Delinquents mouth whereby he is delivered from death. The Lord deales thus with us; he bids us take words, and he alſo ſuggeſts words whereby we may be delivered from iniquity, &amp; received graciouſly, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.2. So <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.19. He deviſeth a way for us how we ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the lengthening of our tranquillitie: It is the Lord
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112637:19"/>that asketh the queſtion: How ſhall I put thee among the children, and give thee a pleaſant land, even a goodly heritage of the hoſtes of nations? And I ſaid, thou ſhalt call me, My Father, and ſhalt not turne away from me: This then is the Lords way that he would have us take, to cry Father, Abba Father, to pray, to devote our ſelves to God, and never to turne from him: No people ever had more encouragements, and more needs then we have to wraſtle with God: O wraſtle with God, leave him not till he bleſſe us: give him not over till we prevaile: when we are Princes and prevailers with God, then ſhall we ſee Mercy and Truth meeting, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Peace kiſſing, then would the Lord be with us in theſe fires, or pull us as brands out of the fire; and then, and not till then we ſhall be prevailers over men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112637:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
